Falnésio Ghander Soares Borges









Phone: +55 (33) 9 2000-5046 Web: http://bit.do/falnesio Residence: Minas Gerais, Brazil

About Me



Bachelor of Economics

sumés in languages of fluency: Português ¡Eng

Graduated in Economic Sciences at the Federal University of Juiz de Fora, Campus GV UFJF - GV and participates in the Center of Agroecology of Governador Valadares NAGO. He is interested in complex systems and believes that models that incorporate the subtleties of social heterogeneity are useful in producing more effective and efficient democratic solutions for socio-economic demands. He also believes that the study of economics has ample room for transdisciplinarity in the formulation of simple, yet more holistic models. He is a very dedicated and focused researcher, who is used to entering new projects and initiatives, adapting to the processes, methodologies, and techniques, accepting challenges and always learning. He works well as a team and always seeks to pass on the knowledge he has acquired.

Education

Universidade Federald e Juiz de Fora -Campus Governador Valadares Bacharelado em Ciências

Emphasizes the training of professionals capable of using the categories of economic thought and the instruments of economic policy for the benefit of society.

2016 - 2020

The graduate of the course can develop activities of planning, forecasting, programming and economic-financial analysis of investments of any nature; studies, analyses, and opinions relevant to economic issues; expertise, assessments, and arbitrations; teaching statistics, economics, and finance in technical and higher education courses; economic consultancy and advice for companies and project development and analysis, as well as economic policy formulation and analysis.

Experience

NAGÔ - Núcleo de Agroecologia de Governador Valadares Scholarship

2018 - present

The main objective of the Nago program is to strengthen Agroecology in the Middle Rio Doce Territory, by supporting extension actions integrated with research and teaching in favor of sustainable rural development, and by overcoming the socio-environmental problems faced by family farmers and traditional peoples and communities of the region, aiming to promote Bem Viver through exchanges of knowledge, practices and agroecological social technologies.

With Nago's support, he had the opportunity to learn and put into practice agroecology, cartography, photography, communication and art, popular and pedagogical; anthropological practice and ethics; popular methods of problem-solving; languages; cultures and traditional spiritualities. As well as learning about the ethno-environmental, politicalhistorical and socio-economic context of traditional peoples.

Rede de Prosumidores Agroecológicos do Médio Rio Doce - promovendo geração de renda familiar, autonomia e soberania a alimentar Scholarship

2018 - presente

This project is linked to the NAGÖ Program (URIP's Center of Agroecology / Governador Valadares Campus), carried out in partnership with the Tamanduá Agroecological Center (CAT), and aims to implement, monitor and promote agroecological based social technologies with rural and urban communities in the Middle Rio Doce Territory. Through participatory methodologies aimed at the exchange of knowledge and the collective construction of knowledge, the extension actions of the project contemplated the theoretical and practical dimensions in the organization of courses, workshops, joint efforts and exchanges covering themes related to social technologies based on agroecology.

The project's activities involve the operational, logistical and financial organization of Rede Tamanduá, a short agri-food chain. Here he produced R algorithms for the analysis of data and documents that assist in planning and management.

Professional Training in Cooperative Management and Marketing of Agroecological Products Voluntary

out. 2016 - 2017

Regional Cooperative for Solidarity Economy, Family Agriculture and Agroecology - Cresala. The production of the incorporated products, as well as in other fields of the socio-economic activity of family production, notably the integration of products and services, supported by agro-industry as well as its processing, commercialization, and consumption, is based on AGROECOLOGY AND THE SOLIDARY POPULAR ECONOMY.

He worked on administrative matters.

CCAA

.ccaa.com.br/unidade/vicosa mai 2012 - nov 2012

For half a century, we operate in the language teaching segment, always offering a high standard of quality. Today, more than 210,000 students worldwide learn English and Spanish at our franchises, through our unique education system.

He taught English classes for the youth and adults at intermediate and advanced levels

Certificates

Curso Intensivo em "Geoprocessamento e Cartografia" nov. 2019 - Univale

Importing Data in R (Part1) mai. 2019 - DataCamp

abr. 2019 - DataCamp

Introduction to the Tidyverse abr. 2019 - DataCamp

The Data Scientist's Toolbox jan. 2019 - Coursera

Extensão universitária em Mercado de Capitais. Usando a Economia a seu favor. 2017 - Universidade Federal de Juiz de Fora, UFJF, Brasil.

Extensão universitária em Bases de Dados. 2017 - Universidade Federal de Juiz de Fora, UFJF, Brasil.

Extensão universitária em II Semana de Econ 2017 - Universidade Federal de Juiz de Fora, UFJF, Brasil

Extensão universitária em Introdução ao Software R. 2017 - Universidade Federal de Juiz de Fora, UFJF, Brasil

Extensão universitária em História e cultura dos povos indígenas de Minas Gerais. Módulo 1. Krenak 2016 - Universidade Federal de Juiz de Fora, UFJF, Brasil

TEP. Teacher Education Program Preservice 2016 - Yázige Valadares, YÁZIGE GV, Brasil

Tráfico de Pessoas, Trabalho Escravo e Migração. ado de Direitos Humanos. Participação Social e Cidadania, SEDPAC, Brasil. 2016 - Secretaria de Estado de Direitos Hum

Events

Encontro de Benzedeiras e Curandeiros do Rio Doce. 2018.

Jornada Intercultural Indígena. 2017.

Production

Map of Agroecological Experiences in the Middle Rio Doce Territory. 2019.

Map of Total Richness of Agroecological Products by Municipality in the Middle Rio Doce Territory. 2019.

Map of Average Area of Agroecological Family Productive Units in the Middle Rio Doce Territory. 2019.

Map of Mean Agroecological Production per Family Unit for each Municipality in the Middle Rio Doce Territory. 2019.

Rede Tamanduá de Prosumidores Agroecológicos: uma Cadeia Agroalimentar Curta em Governador Valadares/MG. In: XI Congresso Brasileiro de Agroecologia, 2019, São Cristóvão/SE. Anais do XI Congresso Brasileiro de Agroecologia, 2019.

Rede Tamanduá de Prosumidores Agroecológicos: promovendo geração de renda familiar, autonomia e soberania alimentar. In: IV Semana de Ciência, Tecnologia e Sociedade da UFJF/GV, 2019, Governador Valadares/MG. Revista de Ciência, Tecnologia e Sociedade da UFJF/GV, 2019. v. 4.

Pluriversidade dos povos e comunidades tradicionais do Watu: Educação Intercultural e Bem Viver no Vale do Rio Doce. In: IV Semana de Ciência, Tecnologia e Sociedade da UFJF/GV, 2019, Governador Valadares/MG. Revista de Ciência, Tecnologia e Sociedade da UFJF/GV, 2019. v. 4.

NAGÔ: Núcleo de Agroecologia de Governador Valadares: semeando a agrobiodiversidade e a transição agroecológica no Território Médio Rio Doce. In: IV Semana de Ciência, Tecnologia e Sociedade da UFJF/GV, 2019, Governador Valadares/MG. Revista de Ciência, Tecnologia e Sociedade da UFJF/GV, 2019. v. 4.

Skills and Attributes

Language

- Simultaneous interpretation EN-PT
 Scientific article translation EN-PT

Programming

- R Python

Technologies

- OGIS
- MySQL
 Microsoft SQL Server · Microsoft PowerPoint
- Microsoft Excel
 Microsoft Windo
 Microsoft Word
- Microsoft Office
- Ubuntu
 LaTex

Interpersonal Abilities

- Presentations
- Teaching Listening

Personal Qualities

- Autodidact
- Focused
 Patient Dedicated